Carlo Domenico Longo de Lemos

Data Scientist @ Experian DataLab LatAm

Linkedln: <u>carlo-lemos</u> Blog: <u>vitaliset.github.io</u> GitHub: <u>github.com/vitaliset</u>

As a Machine Learning specialist, I have led end-to-end projects in the financial sector involving predictive and prescriptive analysis. In addition to my advanced knowledge of probability and statistics, I'm a self-taught Python programmer with excellent computational skills following software engineering best practices. In all my professional experiences, I always promote the sharing of knowledge among peers: whether through the organization and presentation of journal clubs, as well as structuring internal training, study groups, and tutoring juniors and interns.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Experian (credit bureau) | Senior Data Scientist

05/2022 - Present

- I led the development of a Causal Inference model that estimates how the credit default probability of a person changes if we increase his credit card usage. The model was created using covariate adjustment (or S-learner, using <u>causalml</u> meta-learner jargon) and can be used to determine an individual's best credit card limit.
- I helped the insurance team apply domain adaptation techniques (<u>importance weighting</u>) to correct inconsistencies in the development dataset of the life risk classification model. This technique was responsible for a 5-point gain of ROC AUC in our <u>lightgbm.LGBMClassifier</u> model.
- I am currently working on the regression problem of predicting the severity of theft and robbery claims for insurance policies. My model outperforms Experian's benchmarks by over 30% using alternative data sources and a data-centric approach for constructing the development dataset.

Experian (credit bureau) | Data Scientist II

11/2021 - 04/2022

- I led a small team of junior data scientists in developing a Machine Learning model within the AgriScore team.
 We were responsible for building and maintaining a <u>lightgbm.LGBMClassifier</u> credit score aimed at the agricultural market. Activities included:
 - o selecting the correct population of farmers for model development;
 - o restructuring the out-of-time cross-validation framework;
 - o designing business-driven metrics for hyperparameter optimization.

Our team replaced an external data source responsible for 21% of the <u>shap.explainers.Tree.shap_values</u> feature importance of the previous model using Experian internal data and agri-oriented feature selection and engineering.

Itaú Unibanco (bank) | Data Scientist I

11/2020 - 10/2021

- We took advantage of the <u>RCT</u> made by the loan team for pricing studies and developed a causal inference model (<u>matching</u> from <u>sklearn.neighbors.NearestNeighbors</u> of a <u>Leaf Embedding</u> from a <u>sklearn.ensemble.</u>
 <u>RandomForestClassifier</u>) to study the individual elasticity (<u>CATE</u>) of the entire Itaú portfolio. With this project, we created a new pricing dimension in addition to the risk of default in an easy-to-replicate way for other Itaú products impacting more than 30 million customers.
- Applying the same strategy of the loan pricing model, I led a small team of data scientists to develop a model
 that suggests Itaú's managers' goals (how much of each product they should sell that month). From the search
 for similar managers, we were able to spot growth opportunities in certain products and suggest those
 changes. Based on an A/B test, the client area estimated the project's earnings at BRL 452 million per year.

- I was responsible for topic modeling the texts from transcribed calls with a <u>gensim.models.ldamodel</u>.
- I automated some business manual data processes using Python's <u>pandas</u> and HiveQL for querying data with Hadoop.
- I created a <u>sklearn.ensemble.RandomForestClassifier</u> model to predict how likely the client will complain if we have an increase in overdraft price.

EDUCATION

Master's degree in Probability and Statistics | University of São Paulo (USP) - GPA: 4/4 08/2021 - Present

Bachelor's degree in Pure Mathematics | Federal University of ABC (UFABC)

05/2015 - Present

Bachelor's degree in Science and Technology | ABC University (UFABC) - GPA: 3.88/4 05/2015 - 04/2021

OPEN SOURCE SOFTWARE

Data Umbrella's PyMC Open Source Sprint

07/2022

 PyMC is a Bayesian Inference Python library that uses Monte Carlo Markov Chains to sample from posterior distributions. During this sprint, I got to work with my Experian DataLab friend <u>@pibieta</u> on the deprecation of functions, docstring, and minor changes while learning the fundamentals of an Open Source Software community.

TOOLS

-			•				•		
NЛ	~	ch	ın	\sim	^-		~ :	n	\sim
141	~			_	 _	411			u

Classification, Regression, Causal Inference, Anomaly Detection, Clustering, Natural Language Processing.

Python

Good understanding of object-oriented programming and SOLID principles as well as initial knowledge of functional programming. matplotlib, pandas, numpy, abc, collections, itertools, functools, toolz etc.

ML/DS Frameworks

sklearn, statsmodels, tensorflow, nltk, hyperopt, skopt, imblearn, category_encoders, lgbm, xgboost, time-robust-forest, causalml, stable_baselines3, river, aif360 etc.

Database querying

SQL, HiveQL, SASpy, Hadoop.

Backend / Production

Git, Airflow, Docker.

Languages

Portuguese (native) and English (advanced).

RESEARCH FELLOWSHIPS

FAPESP (São Paulo Research Foundation) Wada Property in Doubly Transient Chaos

11/2018 - 09/2019

FAPESP (São Paulo Research Foundation)

09/2017 - 08/2018

The Euler-Maclaurin formula and a few applications in Pure and Applied Mathematics

CNPQ (Brazilian National Council for Research and Technological Development)

Numerical study of orbits in the 3-body problem

08/2016 - 07/2017

UFABC, Researching Since the First Day Program Introduction to stellar structure and evolution

08/2015 - 07/2016

OTHER PROJECTS

Vitali Set <u>vitaliset.github.io</u>

Vitali Set is my site about Machine Learning (posts in portuguese only for now).

Journal Club presentations

vitaliset/talks

- Some of the talks I like the most:
 - <u>Multiarmed bandits problems</u>: discussed how to approach the problem, both Bernoulli and non-Bernoulli, with drift or context, using epsilon-greedy, UCB, and Thompson Sampling.
 - Out of distribution generalization: on how to perform well across different environments, even if you only have a few in your training data.
 - <u>Leaf Embedding</u>: using bagging of trees to find a distance between samples that focus on features relevant to the problem you are trying to solve and are scale-independent.
 - Symbolic Regression: we can create a population of functions and measure their fitness using a
 performance metric. Using Darwin's idea of natural selection (survival of the fittest), we can refine the
 individuals to get a good estimator with explicit expression.

Imbalanced Binary Classification: A Survey with code

pibieta/imbalanced_learning

Together with my Experian DataLab friends <u>Alessandro</u> and <u>Pablo</u>, we wrote some chapters on approaching imbalanced binary classification. In particular, I discussed <u>model interpretability</u> under these scenarios.

INTERESTS

causal inference, machine learning fairness, out-of-distribution generalization (including dataset shift, but not only), model interpretability, statistical learning theory, online learning, (contextual) multi-armed bandits, reinforcement learning, black-box optimization, adversarial training, software engineering best practices, open-source etc.